[Music]
welcome today we will talk about
business Central and Power Platform my
name is buaji Koto I work as a product
manager in business Central Development
Center in
Copenhagen and hello everyone my name is
Monica alja I'm a senior software
engineer in business Central team here
in
Copenhagen today we'll cover various
aspects of business Central integration
with power platforms starting with power
automate power apps data vers virtual
tables we'll mention of course power
pages powerbi and so on and uh that all
starts uh with business Central being
and running in Microsoft cloud and
working closely together with all those
Microsoft cloud services like Microsoft
365 Azure Power Platform and Dynamics
365 and of course for that for the
context of this session we will be
looking at Power Platform Power Platform
for those of you who don't know is a set
of low code development tools tools that
help you enhance business Central uh and
create new experience for customers and
that might be powerbi where you can
build business analytics charts reports
and dashboards power apps where you can
build uh mobile or desktop apps power
automate that allows you to create
automations workflows and various other
automated tasks uh then we have also
power virtual agents which is a tool
allowing you to build chatbot
experiences um virtual uh agents uh plug
them into your websites into teams and
into your apps and then uh last but not
least power pages and new uh tool from
Power Platform family allowing you to
build websites that are externally
available and all of that works on top
of data verse data verse being
Microsoft's data management platform and
uh works together with connectors so
connectors are are a very important
component of Power Platform allowing you
to build connectivity to various systems
and that includes Microsoft's products
but also third party products and of
course course business Central uh
connectors are in that group and as you
can see in this wave we actually and
changed the icon theme for the business
Central connectors so now it is easier
for you to distinguish the online
version from the all their on premises
business Central
connector let's start with power
automate and the enhancements we have
done in that area and that all starts
from the way you create flow
you know that in business Central you
have the automate group in most of the
pages and that's that's where power
automate integration is located and
right now in this wave we created very
easy way to distinguish between between
those three different ways of creating
power automate
flows you will you will see approval
workflows so the on pages that support
uh approvals for instance sales order
you will see an action to create an
approval uh workflow you will see also a
new uh entry point a new action allowing
you to create automated flows those
flows that run in the background and are
able to react on various events that
might be business events coming from
business Central but it might be also
some events coming from outside like for
instance a message an email that you
have
received and then the third option is
something that you are familiar with but
we Chang the name a little bit to make
sure you it's easy to understand that
this creates an action in business
Central action bar that starts a power
automate flow uh and then can automate
something that that that you need to
automate in business Central all of
those are features enabled in feature
management so if you have a business
Central tenant or environment that has
been upgraded from previous version make
sure that you turn on uh this uh
integration with power automate and
templates in future management uh if you
have if you're creating a new uh
environment in business Central or a
Sandbox environment with preview version
of business Central
2023 wave two this is enabled by default
and this is enabled on by default for
you and as you see we have a lot of
templates and we're talking about
templates because we want to focus you
uh or Focus your attention on templates
and we are giving you a lot of templates
and I think Monica has something to say
about those right BL so in this release
we have not only improved the existing
templates but we have also added a lot
of new templates in all the categories
of flows so for example uh we have added
a request approval flow for sales order
entity where previously you would set
the approval request by email but in
this one you could also send adaptive
card and teams we have added 17 new
automated templates that are based on
external business events uh so these
templates allow to allow the
notification on teams whenever an
external business event happens for
example a customer is blogged or a
purchase order is released and so on we
have also added new instant templates
you you might have already seen the
block the selected scenario in instant
templates now we have added three more
which includes scheduling a visit
creating summary email and summarizing
inventory for item from all the
companies so so that that was about the
templates thank you
Monica when we talking about templates
uh you can create a flow based on the
template and actually as you have seen
we have plenty new templates in the Box
we will be for sure adding more but you
might want to edit that template and and
uh uh create some adjustments to it and
we will see that later on in the demo
the templates that we uh that we
provided for approvals have been also
changed so they are not completely new
but they have been uh changed and some
new capabilities are added to those I
think it will be best to show it in a
demo Monica yeah let's see the demo for
the simplified automate approval
template
experience so let's start with the flow
that I created based on an existing
approval template and as you can see it
is massive so let me just zoom
in so uh we are made plenty of
improvements in this uh template let's
start with the first one previously the
the requestor uh that would show up for
the approver will always be the creator
of the flow no matter who actually
requested the approval request so now we
have improved that by actually adding
the real requesters email in the uh
approval action but not only that we are
actually getting all the details of the
requester and passing it along in the
mail that the approver gets so approver
knows who the requester is that's one of
the improvements that we have made to
this template another one is now we are
supporting the cancel scenario uh apart
from approve and reject so we have Expos
the cancel action as the endo and uh now
when the requestor cancels the approval
for any reason then that will be also
supported please remember that these
templates are just the basis uh or
examples that you can start from you can
always modify anything on these
templates as per your need let's say for
example you can add an action where you
want to add an item to a SharePoint so
you could just go ahead and click in
action and change as per the need so in
this case we will go and search for
SharePoint and we can say uh I would
like to create an item on the SharePoint
so that's how it simple it is thank you
Monica that was very interesting as you
have seen Monica is creating some
additional experiences in those
templates and playing with the maker
experience and we made it much easier in
this wave to manipulate flows and create
flows that uh later on when you run them
uh are working with different companies
and different
environments yes you're right BL so in
this way you don't even need to specify
company to list API categories or tables
for any action or trigger of the
connector but not only that you actually
get all the metadata details without
specifying the company so now you can
use just a standard variable for for
specifying the company ID and then make
flows that can run in context of
different companies uh we also support
the use of data was environment
variables for environments which means
that uh uh now that the Alm story for
algo for GitHub also supports
environment
variables but talking about companies
and environments what other Improvement
have we done we have now added a new
action in the connector called list
companies it allows you to get all the
business Central companies for a given
environment so basically now you can
enable flows that flows data across the
companies let me just quickly show you a
demo for this to show you all the
improvements that we have done for the
maker experience I'm starting with the
solution where I have defined an
environmental variable called BC
environment and as you have seen that we
I have also added a default value of my
current production name to this so let's
see how how we can use this for better
makers experience I'll go ahead and
create an instant
flow and we can now look for the new
action that we have
added it's called list
companies and you can see that it only
asks for environment as an input and
provides the list of companies for that
environment and normally you could just
add the predefined environments but uh
you could now also use the environment
variable that data was provides so in
this case I'm going to do that and let's
see how the further metadata is
created so right now I'm just going
ahead and creating
record and you can see that uh I can use
the environment variable again for the
environment but now without even
specifying the company I can already
fetch the API categories this wasn't
possible before and not only that I can
also fetch the tables that are available
for this API category and all the
metadata that exist for that particular
table so that what does that mean that
means now we can use the normal
variables to Define this but not only
that we can also use the output of list
company so we can go through each of
this company to create a record in any
all of these companies so in this case I
am using the output from list companies
and that's how simple now creating a
flow is thank you Monica that was super
interesting imagine what you can build
right now with those new tools one more
thing that we added to the connector we
have added that already around some
summer time so you can you could have
seen that in the connector is an trigger
to react on business events the concept
of business events is is new in business
Central and it's still in preview but
that allows you to react on special code
or special events that happen in your
code we have created several uh business
events from in our app from Microsoft
but you as a partner are able to create
a new event using a new Al construct and
then you use a power automate trigger
when a business event occurs or if
you're using virtual tables if you're
visualizing our data you can also use
the data verse trigger uh and react on
those business events uh that event
passes a specific context to power
automate for instance a document ID this
business event can be triggered from any
company it could be a specific company
or all companies so you can react on a
specific business event coming from any
company in a given environment that can
be quite powerful super and connector
also supports latest versions of
business events right yes I've heard
about that let's see that in action yes
let's see the demo for this for this
demo we will start with business Central
client so we'll start with the single
Consolidated place for creating
approvals based on templates that BL had
referred in the previous slides and you
can see there are three three options
available for business events based
templates we will select create
automated flow and now it opens a
template Gallery where you can see all
the templates for the given entity that
are based on automated flow is something
similar that will also happen for other
actions but that will be based on
instant or approvals depending on the
action you have chosen so in this case
we right now have two templates that uh
will that basically notifies on teams
whenever a customer is blocked or
unblocked so basically whenever these
particular business events happen let me
just go ahead and create a flow based on
one of these
templates so this one is smart enough to
recognize what are the connections
needed so it's only business Central and
teams to
notify and then basically it ask you
which team and channel you want to uh
get notified to when the customer is
blocked so let's just go ahead and
select Communications team and then it
will pop up all the channels available
it's only General so let's select that
and click create flow that's how simple
it was to create the
template so now we will just go ahead
and block the
customer so I'll
block this one as you can see this is
not blocked so we'll just go ahead and
block
it and let's see what happens on the
team side so on the team side you can
see that I have received an Adaptive
card which gives me the details of the
customer card and it also adds a special
header that says customer has been
blocked let's see how it looks on the
automate
site so here here you can see a new flow
has been created for notifying on teams
when a customer is blocked let's just
see what are the details of this flow so
you can see that this flow is based on
the when a business event occurs which
is an trigger that we use to identify
all the business events in this case we
are saying customer blocked but there's
also the business all other business
events that are available out of the box
and as a partner you can also add more
business events and then it will
automatically recognize those available
business
events but what else is there we're now
extracting the particular customer who
is blocked and then we are getting the
Adaptive card but now we're doing a
small trick to actually change the
output of the Adaptive card card which
allows us to add the header saying that
the customer is blocked and then we are
posting it in the channel that's how
simple it is thank you let's have a look
at few other things so this first one is
about uh notifications that come from
business Central to power automate based
on web hooks before there was a limit of
100 rows only and right now it's uh
1,000 so we changed that 10f and that
allows you to build flows that react on
bulk changes when you change a lot of
data at the same time and that of course
opens new scenarios the other thing that
we want would like to mention is V2
actions you have seen in our connector
that are actions the current actions
called V3 and then of course some old
actions uh designated V2 from December
this year all of those V2 actions will
be hidden and you won't be able to see
them again uh but for the flows that are
running that are in production this they
will continue to work we are not
disturbing you but if you edit the edit
those flows you will have to update to
version three we would actually
encourage you uh to to do it before
December and change and update your
flows and always use the latest versions
of the of the actions so this change
this this this notification or the
change of this uh will be happening in
December okay let's switch there to
powerups we talk about power apps and
two different types of power apps that
work with business Central we're talking
about canvas apps where you have full
control over the UI but you have to
build that UI and that's those types of
power apps are usually uh designed for
mobile experience for desktop for phones
or tablets and then they work with
business Central through our connector
all through dataverse virtual tables and
then the second type of the power apps
is model driven apps which are based on
a database model and that requires data
versus virtual tables but let's talk
about the canvas apps the apps that are
designed for mobile and we have added
some interesting things in this wave to
uh to the experience for for partners
yes Monica that's absolutely right BL
not only we have updated the
documentation but in this release we are
adding new sample apps so you can get
started fast and we are also providing
the get started guidance on how to make
the app look good easy to maintain and
properly engineer let's talk about data
vers virtual tables this is a technology
that allows you to virtualize data from
business Central so that it appears in
data verse almost as native tables and
then of course it allows you to build
Rich Integrations with dataverse apps or
apps that are running on data verse and
that might be other Dynamic 365 apps but
but it might be also some custom app
apps that you have built in this wave we
made it much easier to get started so
when you are when you are starting from
business Central you go to assisted
setup and you enable data vers virtual
tables right now you can easily choose
which virtual tables or which tables
would you would like to visualize and
just enable them uh one by one or even
you can select multiple and enable them
uh in uh from within business Central
what is also important that this
technology virtual tables for business
Central uh is going to be generally
available later this year so you can
start building more robust uh Solutions
based on that
technology speaking of virtual tables we
need to mention power Pages power pages
is a new product coming from from Power
Platform and in later in this year we
will um deliver a preview version of our
integration Based on data vers virtual
tables that means you will be able to
build uh portals or uh websites that are
exposed externally that are available to
your customer so think about B2B
scenarios uh because power Pages enables
uh authenticated access for external
users and there is a way of map those
external users to your customers you can
think about building portals where your
customer can see data related to them
only we will provide more details around
this technology around November time
frame H and of course this will be a a
preview optin experience at the
beginning and we will be looking for
feedback from you Partners through our
Yammer Community we will talk about
Yammer in a moment you will also find a
separate recording uh talking about
power pages and data vers virtual tables
and this technology in this uh event
let's talk about powerbi in powerbi uh
embed experience which you will see in
business Central we have made some
significant changes to make it easier
for you to control what you see and how
you see especially when you see uh
reports of dashboards that are full
screen or larger you can control uh how
the page opens up uh you control control
the zoom level you can control pages and
those pages are remembered so it's
easier to return back to your specific
report that you choose we also support
powerbi scorecard so right now if you
built a scorecard it is also view
viewable from within business Central
and we also added some
uh components in Al that allow you to
control that from your code from Al code
and there is also a separate recording
in this event that talks about this
experience to summarize in business
Central integration with Power Platform
we offer multiple Technologies starting
with powerbi and powerbi connector
through our standard Core Power Platform
connector allowing you to work with
power apps power automate Azure logic
apps as well and of course uh the rest
of Power Platform we offer data vers
virtual tables that
virtualizes uh data into Data verse that
supports that will support power pages
natively as I mentioned a moment ago and
then we also offer data sync which is a
technology that allows you to sync data
to data verse and that is mostly to
connect to other thir uh Dynamics 365
products if you have any questions about
the that integration we have a special
Yammer group for Power Platform and data
verse on our in our Yammer community of
course we are always in our social media
Twitter X LinkedIn and so on
uh if you're looking for anything aka.
m/b is your link and of course always
submit ideas through our ideas site we
have also uh couple of times a year um
open Office hours or office hour calls
for Power Platform and uh there is one
in the next couple of months so please
tune in to those and ask any questions
related to Power Platform integration
over there and I think that will be it
from us in this recording thank you very
much thank
you